This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SE-Radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Digital Ocean recently launched Spaces,
a beautifully simple object storage
service designed for developers who want
a simple way to store and serve a vast
amount of data, such as images and large
media files, user-generated content,
backups, and logs. Spaces is available
for a simple $5 per month price that
includes 250 GB of storage and 1 TB of
outbound bandwidth. Additional storage
is priced at the lowest rate available,
1 cent per GB transferred and 2 cents
per GB stored. This provides cost
savings of up to 10 times along with
predictable pricing and no surprises on
your monthly bill. Try it for free with
a 2-month trial by going to
do.co/seradio.
This is Nate Black for Software
Engineering Radio. I'm very pleased to
welcome Ron Lichty, co-author of
Managing the Unmanageable to the show.
Recruited to Apple in 1988, Ron product
managed Apple's development tools, then
led the Finder and Applications groups
for the Apple II and Macintosh product
lines, managing delivery of Apple's user
interface.
Ron went on to direct development of
entertainment products at Berkeley
Systems and Fujitsu, specializing in
making development predictable and
repeatable.
Ron then led software development of
schwab.com's first online investment
tools. Since Schwab, he has had vice
president roles in engineering and
products, both as an employee and as a
consultant.
Ron has given a conference and
professional group talks on implementing
Agile and Scrum and transforming
software development from chaos to
clarity.
Ron, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio.
Thanks, Nate.
Your book, Managing the Unmanageable,
talks about programming managers in
contrast to other kinds of managers.
Could you define what is a programming
manager?
Well, a programming manager is a manager
who manages programmers, and the um the
challenge is that my co-author, Mickey
Mantle, and I think that
programmers are that we who who are or
have been programmers are pretty unique
bunch. Um we tend to refer to ourselves
as software engineers, but
while there is some engineering aspects
to what we do, there's also art to what
we do. It's no weird thing that there's
a huge crossover between software
developers and musicians. The number of
programmers who also do music is is is
really huge.
And interestingly, music has both a left
brain and a right brain kind of aspect
to it. It has a very very analytical uh
way that it's put together and a very
artful way to deliver it to delight
customers.
When we're in the software business, our
goal is to delight customers, but we
have to be very analytical about it as
well as artful.
And that combination of engineering and
artfulness or engineering and craft is
pretty unusual. Uh electronics
engineering is very cut and dried,
mechanical engineering is very cut and
dried, uh aeronautical engineering is
very cut and dried, civil engineering is
very cut and dried.
Software engineering, not so much. We
start with thought stuff.
We conjure up a pro in in uh I have
friends who are novelists who say, you
know, writing software is a lot like
writing a novel.
You start with a blank page and craft it
from there.
Part of the challenge of being a
programming manager is
the nature of the work itself, but also
the fact that programmers themselves are
different. Could you talk a little bit
more about that?
You know, so the challenge in managing
us and managing programmers is that not
only are we different from everyone
else, but we're different from each
other. So,
programmers are different from every
everyone else in
the sense of being both left-brained and
right-brained in both being both
engineers and crafts people.
And we have to motivate and to enable
both parts of brains, both parts of who
programmers are.
And we also have to think about how how
programmers differ from each other, not
not just how they differ from other
groups of people, but how they differ
from each other.
You know, in our book, uh we slice and
dice us into in in various ways to try
to be helpful in understanding who we
are.
So, web developers are different
database developers are different from
systems developers are different from
business logic developers are different
from scripters.
Uh there are morning people and night
people. There are farmers and cowboys.
There are so many ways to think about it
and ultimately every programmer is
unique and the challenge for us as
managers is to figure out that
uniqueness
of each of the people who work for us
and to truly connect with and support
and enable each of those each of those
qualities and each of those people.
Is it correct to say that the manager is
responsible for
managing people and their careers or are
there other responsibilities?
For instance, do you managers write
code?
Uh so, do managers write code? So,
that's a that's a great question. The
answer is that there are plenty of
managers who do write code. What Mickey
and I would say about that is that
if you're managing and you're writing
code and that code is is critical path
code, you are likely to focus on one of
those things or the other and you're
likely to do
at most one of them well and then
possibly neither of them well.
Um they're very different qualities. Um
the the transition from programming the
actually the transition through a career
path
Um one of the rules of thumb is that
this the very thing that makes you
successful at one level gets in your way
at the next.
So think about what does it take to be a
great programmer? One of the
characteristics that makes you great at
being a programmer is the ability to
shut out the world
to climb into the microprocessor and
listen to the gates open and close
to truly become one with the computer
and that's just exactly the opposite of
what you need to do as a manager. As a
manager you need to not only put a a
welcome mat out in front of your door
but to proactively
welcome interruptions from the people
who work for you
from your peers and from your boss
because all of that stuff is what you're
managing and trying to create with the
people who work for you teamwork and
motivation and
uh or to get out of the way of their own
motivation and it's it's a really a
people kind of job with a technical kind
of background.
You've talked before about the need for
a programmers to focus on their work and
focus being an important part but you
just mentioned that
managers are taking interruptions all
the time. So it seems that their
priorities are in a way flipped from
what a programmer's priorities are. Is
that right?
Yeah, so a manager's priorities are
their programmers.
And I, as a manager, need to be aware of
and available to my team pretty much all
the time.
Why is programming management hard?
Well,
to start with,
to be a good programming manager, you
almost have to have been a programmer
before that. Much as
football coaches and basketball coaches
and tennis coaches played the game, with
very rare exceptions, before becoming
that coach, we as managers are
essentially coaches of our teams.
And knowing what it is that our
teams face, what it is that the people
who are on our teams face, and what what
it is that bring them together to cause
great stuff to happen
is is a real challenge. One of the
things that that I just cited was that
change from
climbing from from shutting out the
world to inviting the world to interrupt
us, one of the things that makes that
hard is that
some very large percentage of us who are
programmers are introverts.
And what we need to do is learn
extroversion skills.
What we need to learn is people
relationship skills. What we need to
learn is
empathy skills,
that soft stuff, that emotional
intelligence stuff
that makes people comfortable talking to
us because fundamentally that's what we
want is our teams to talk to us and to
tell us what's important and what's
getting in their way and how we can
help.
How much training do managers usually
have before they're thrown into the
fire, so to speak?
Uh great question. I have talked to
audiences of now probably thousands of
managers
and it's a question that I ask to find
out exactly how much management training
I'm seeing in my audience.
And I'll have everybody in the audience
who's a manager stand up.
And I will ask those who have
had at least one day of training in
management. Just one.
To stay standing.
Half my audience will sit down.
Almost universally, half my audience
sits down. And then I'll ask those of
you who've had those of you all of you
standing have had at least one day of
training in management. This is not
managing programmers. This is just
something related to management.
If you had a day of that training before
you became a manager, stay standing.
We're looking at 5% or less of managers
who've had a day of training. It's
really ironic the amount of training we
expect programmers to have in
programming and the the lack of training
that we expect of managers.
You also pointed out that many
programming managers fall into the job
almost without any planning, almost as
if it happens by accident.
So becoming a manager is not something
we get to decide. We can we can train
for it. We could plan for it. We could
prepare for it. We could think this is
my career path.
But it's somebody else who decides
whether we get an offer to be a manager
and that managerhood offer could come
because our manager quits and his
manager says, "Ron, you've got some
people skills. You manage the team." And
that happens more often than not in
talking with a lot of managers.
You were just tapped to become the
manager and and you're stepping into a
role that
you haven't you may have given it some
thought but you certainly haven't given
it the kind of thought that it deserves.
What should you think about before you
accept that role and step into this new
role?
You want to think about what it is that
you want to do and what you like to do.
And and I would suggest think about
trying it out. You know, we do in in
modern
management in modern project management
we talk about process experiments and
you know, I think this is this is
without
given lack of manager
candidates you may be the best shot your
team's got at having a good manager.
Um so that would be one thing to think
about is am I the am I the best shot my
team's got for having a manager because
that could make a really big difference.
And then think about let me try this out
and think about it. So my own transition
to being a manager was uh well I was I
was intrigued by I was interested in
becoming a manager.
I uh was a programmer. I had what I
thought was the best job in the whole
world. I was in a two-person programming
shop. We were doing everything from
embedded microcontrollers to
compiler code generators to multimedia
entertainment applications and early
word processing software.
And I was really intrigued by gee, I
wonder what managing a group of people
like me would be like. And I was
thinking about that and and it was
really the only reason that I wanted to
leave this two-person shop was I
couldn't become a manager in a
two-person shop.
And there was one other company I was
interested in working for really
interested in working for and that was
Apple Computer and Apple made me an
offer to come be a manager.
And I said sure.
Yes, I'll come do that. In fact, I was
not managing developers. I was asked to
come manage create a product management
group in a technical
in a technical sense, a product
management group of development tools
inside of Apple Computer.
And I spent uh, about a year and a half
being a manager in that product
management organization before Apple in
those days and probably still reorgs
pretty incessantly and and about a year
and a half in, they reorged my job out
of existence and said, "Go looking for
another job inside of Apple."
And I thought about it and thought,
"This has been interesting. I'm going to
be a programmer again."
I went back to being a programmer.
Uh, it was I don't think I was a
programmer for more than a month or two
before they made me the manager.
Uh, 6 months later they blew up that
group. I went looking for another
programming job. About a month or two
later they made me the manager. It was
only that third time being a manager
that I truly felt like this is what I
wanted to do. It's very different role
programming and managing programmers.
And, you know, I think you get really
have to think about the tradeoffs are
that as a programmer, you're working on
code, you're working on making thought
stuff work. You're working on hard
technical challenges and when you
succeed, it's so ecstatically
wonderful that you jump out of your
chair and scream with delight. At least
I have.
And you don't get that as a manager. You
don't get the same ecstatic excitement
and and joy coming from achieving and
you you also don't get quite the same
level of despair
uh, right before you hit that level of
joy.
But as a manager, you've got much more
breadth, you've got more say in the
game, you've got say about any
particular thing.
You've got less ability to dive deep,
but you've got way more ability to dive
broad. And it's it's just a fundamental
decision of where you want to spend your
time and how do you want to spend your
time. Do you want to spend your time
helping a whole group of people to get
that ecstatic joy?
Or do you want to be the one getting the
joy?
For a programmer, that joy comes from,
as you said, putting code out that
works. But what does success look like
for a manager? How do you judge yourself
on have I been successful?
Uh it's a much less measurable kind of
result, but it's it's a feeling
that I've got a team that's really
really on the same wavelength. That a
team that's really gelling, a team
that's really becoming a
high-performance team.
And I've helped to enable that. I've
I've helped people to see what their
connection is to the bigger picture.
I've helped people to see how what
they're doing is delighting customers.
I've helped people to see how working
together we can get more synergy and
more power and more success than we can
just working as individuals.
I've helped people to see how to have
each other's backs and do respect and
trust and and
really come together as a team, not just
a group of individuals.
And there's uh huge amount of
gratification
that comes from looking at your team and
realizing that you've done that.
So you talked about what success looks
like as a manager, but in your book you
also described the pointy-haired boss.
And that's kind of an archetype for
what a bad manager looks like. What is a
pointy-haired boss?
Yeah, well, the pointy-haired boss comes
out of Dilbert and it and it and it's
the boss none of us, hopefully,
hopefully no one listening to this show
wants to be the pointy-eared boss.
We're all trying to be the the opposite
of that archetype. We're trying to be
the boss who truly
who
programmers come away and say,
"It was great working for Ron. If he
ever calls me again to work on one of
his teams, I'm going to go do that
because it was it was a peak experience
for me."
Is it a matter of avoiding doing certain
bad things, or is it something positive
you have to go after, or a combination?
Oh, absolutely a combination.
We managers need to figure out how to
set boundaries without without
micromanaging. How to set goals without
telling people what to do and how to do
it.
How to enable them to own
pieces of the code that they're working
on
and
bring their best selves to that code and
bring all of their thinking and their
options and
possibilities to that code and to create
something
better
and to delight customers in ways that
they didn't expect to be delighted.
Can you describe what happens when a
manager tells a programmer what to do
and and also how to do it?
One of the examples that I give of what
we have to avoid in Agile, Agile asks
everybody on a team to step up. It asks
teams to come together as teams.
And what micromanagement does is it
causes people to step back.
Uh if I'm a programmer and I've got
somebody telling me what to do and how
to do it, I'm going to step back and and
say, "Okay, I've got that done. What do
you want me to do next? What do you want
me to do next? What do you want me to do
next?" I'm going to become an order
taker instead of bringing my whole self
to both the product and to my team.
And it's really counterproductive. It's
really counterproductive on the part of
managers.
And part of bringing your whole self is
also bringing that right brain aspect
that you're talking about the
creativity. Is Do you have an example of
something that a programmer contributed
that just was
out of left field they weren't expecting
to made a positive impact?
I'll bring an example of my own. When I
was a programmer, we were doing a brand
new device that didn't exist yet.
And the inventor of that device
Uh this was a this was both electronics
and software and I was working on the
software part of it that was going to be
embedded in this device.
And the inventor of the device came to
us with a manual for his device.
This is what I'm going to give to users.
This is how the thing works. You guys
figure out how to do how to how to
create the guts.
How to make this thing deliver what it
is that I'm asking for.
And it was possibly the only project I
ever worked on as a programmer and
possibly the only one I've seen since
that there were no ambiguities in what
he wanted. It was really clear the what
was really clear. But he wasn't giving
us any of the how. He was saying, you
know, bring yourselves to this and and
give give me the best that you can give
me.
And the what was so clear that it was
like rolling down a hill delivering what
he wanted and I had time left over to
bring that right brain left brain stuff
you were just talking about. I invented
a way of storing that data. This is very
early on when there was very little
memory and the kind of storage spaces
that we were doing and I invented a new
way of doing that and and he got a
patent on the encryption method that I
invented for doing that and it was
because he didn't tell me how to do it.
It was because he only said, "Here's
what I imagine I want to deliver for my
customers."
Do you think that most of the time
that information or those requirements
or goals
or even values aren't communicated down
clearly enough to the developers? Is Is
that the cause of a lot of problems that
we see?
Communication in every way is one of the
big problems that I run into just over
and over and over again. Fundamentally,
software development, fundamentally
product development is a team sport.
And we need to talk to each other. So,
we you know, one of the big chasms
is between the people who wear the title
product manager and the people who wear
the title developers and testers.
And
the what we need is to understand the
what without
without being told the how, but we need
to understand as much of the what as
possible.
And we need to understand really what it
is that what problem it is that our
customers are trying to solve
and how they're struggling with it and
what that really represents.
And then we need to apply our brains to
it as developers and testers to come up
with options
that our product managers can look at
and say, "Oh, that one will will blow
our customers away." Fundamentally,
there's Uh well, so we've got a rule of
Mickey and I came up with a rule of
thumb that you can't over-communicate in
product teams.
Now, it's possible that on the sales
side they can over-communicate. It's
possible on the marketing side they can
over-communicate, but I'm pretty sure
that in product development we can't
over-communicate.
Many organizations use the Scrum or
Agile process for that communication
between the team and the product
managers. And you pointed out in one of
your talks that in the Agile diagram,
the manager isn't even depicted. So,
that brings up the question, if we're
Agile, why do we need managers?
coach in Scandinavia, name of Henrik
Kniberg, who
has done some work in Scrum with
Spotify, actually, and has written about
that, and he's got some diagrams that
basically show teams being
self-organizing and self-sufficient
in a lot of ways.
What are not self-sufficient are the
groups of people within them. So, we
create these cross-functional teams that
have web developers and business logic
developers and database developers and
product managers and and Scrum Masters
and testers and sometimes DBAs and and
other
other functions in them.
And there's our team, and that team can
deliver business value to customers, but
what it can't do is the care and feeding
of the function of the
of the the kind of work doesn't happen
inside of that team. The database
developers need best practices. The
database developers need to grow their
careers, and if within their teams, they
continue to be focused on delivering
stuff to customers, they won't be
focused on growing their careers, on
growing their ability in their field, on
communicating across teams with the
other people who do what they do, and to
best practices, and it you know, how we
use best practices and how we how we
leverage standards and and how we do
stuff in a in in effective way within
our particular specialty.
And what managers do is to feed all of
that and support all of that. And it's a
I think of it Think of it as, you know,
there we we've talked about matrixed
organizations, and I'm not sure that
this is is exactly a matrixed
organization in the classic sense, but
it's definitely a matrixed organization
from the standpoint that teams are
self-organizing,
but the web developers report to
somebody who did web development, whose
job it is not to tell them what to do,
but to enable them and support them in
in their growth and in their best
practices and in their communications
across their specialty
to uh to doing their best work.
That goes back to your coach analogy,
where the manager is like a coach
and making sure that the team is
structured the right way, maybe that
they're
they have individuals that fill all the
different skill and various roles,
and also that they're progressing in the
way they need to progress in order to
get better at their game.
Yeah, yeah. I I'm not a sports guy.
I'm really not a sports guy, but when I
was at Schwab in 1999 or 2000, I had a
management coach who thrust a sports guy
book into my hands. So, the book was
Sacred Hoops by Phil Jackson.
Phil Jackson, I no idea who Phil Jackson
was, but it turns out Phil Jackson was
the coach of the Chicago Bulls at the
time. Since then been the the coach of
the LA Lakers. At that time had won a
number of NBA records with the uh with
the Chicago Bulls, and since then
between the Bulls and the Lakers has won
11 rings
on his hand. And his goal was to create
a self-organizing basketball team. So,
this is a guy who inherited
Michael Jordan.
He inherited a number of other players,
too, but I hadn't heard of them.
You All of you probably have, but I
hadn't heard of them. But I had heard of
Michael Jordan. He inherited Michael
Jordan. Michael Jordan had set every
shooting record that existed, it seemed
like.
And the Chicago Bulls were not winning.
His goal was to create a team in which
Michael Jordan was part of the team, and
everyone else didn't just stand back and
look at Michael Jordan in awe, but they
actually played together, and they
worked together, and they passed the
ball together.
Phil Jackson, and so, you know, I played
a little bit of basketball when I was in
middle school, which is why I really
don't think about basketball because I
swore it off after middle school.
But, I remember thinking, "Gee, you
know, the we get in trouble out there on
the court, what we do is turn and look
at the coach."
Phil Jackson's method was, "I want you
guys to look at each other."
My goal in practice is to guide your
work so that when you get into trouble,
you look at each other. You look to each
other. And he says in one of those two
books, he says, "When my team is firing,
not only does the other team not know
what my team is going to do next, my
team doesn't know what it's going to do
next. They watch each other, and they
play off of each other."
If you think about that, that's that's
like improv in acting, or it's like free
jazz in music, where every single member
of an improv team, and every single
member of of a free jazz group
is a soloist from time to time, but they
play off of each other, and no one knows
when their solo's going to come up for
sure.
I love that analogy with the Chicago
Bulls and Michael Jordan because it
touches on what you said in your book
about the distribution of skills in a
team, and how there are certain
programmers that make outsized
contributions,
but that may not be enough in order to
have a successful team and to launch a
successful product. But, I would like
you to talk a little bit about that as
we dive into teams and building a team.
Can a good manager
take any group of individuals and turn
it into a successful team?
Well, so one of the
We were talking earlier about categories
of
programmers and there's a category that
I would that Mickey and I labeled jerks
and bozos.
There is a category of that probably in
every category of work and
when we're building teams and software
development is fundamentally a team
sport, I'm going to come back to that.
Bozos and jerks do not fit on teams. So,
can I take any group of people and make
them into a team?
Probably not.
Can I take someone who's acting like a
jerk or a bozo and have a conversation
with them about the fact that we're not
going to have that on our team and do
they want to not be that and be on a
team or do they want to leave? Yes, I
can do that and I will do that and I
have done that.
Because the team needs me to do that.
Every team knows who those people are
and
cringes
when they evoke that kind of behavior.
How do you build a successful team?
Mickey and I started writing our book
because we had been having breakfast
with each other. We'd been mentoring
each other
over breakfast
every couple of months
for years and had been sharing rules of
thumb over the breakfast table with each
other and thought
these are really valuable to us. Maybe
we ought to collect them and share them
with other managers.
And then it occurred to us maybe we
ought to use the 60 years or so of
experience we had in software
development and share a little bit of
that, too. So, that took us another 8
years to write.
Those rules of thumb, one of one of
those is from a guy named David Vidra,
who is a bit of a guru
in test-driven development and testing
and Agile.
And David's got a rule of thumb that
pair programming for half an hour with a
candidate during an interview will save
everyone's a huge amount of time.
And what happens during pair programming
with a candidate is that we learn how
the candidate programs,
but we also learn how they collaborate.
And we also learn whether this is
someone we want to work with.
And I think that's a really valuable way
of
of recruiting and and interviewing and
identifying
people who will work and become part of
our team.
Rich Sheridan, who runs
Menlo Innovations, an Agile-based
consulting company out of Ann Arbor,
Michigan,
uses that to the max.
Uh he talks about how
uh Menlo Innovations will bring in 50
candidates for per 50 programming
candidates at a time.
They will pair them up with each other
and have as a third person a a watcher,
essentially, a a fly on the wall
watching
these two people pair with each other,
and the goal of pairing
for each of those 50 people is to get
their pair hired.
Not to get themselves hired, to get
If you can make your pair look so good
that we want to hire him or her, we're
likely to want to hire you, too.
You know, I think that's what we have to
think about as managers, as hiring
managers, as people recruiting
developers, are who can work with the
people on our team and yeah, effectively
and
and and really team up.
And is that also a measure of a
good successful employee that they're
making their peers look good,
not just making themselves look good?
Yeah, I absolutely and another measure
of that would be how am I ensuring that
my peers know what I know.
So, every single member of a team, even
those hired just hired out of college,
have unique expertise and unique
experience.
And our goal as managers is to foment
the cross-pollination of that
expertise and that experience and every
member of that team should be thinking
about what do I know that would be
useful to my teammates to know and how
do I share it?
Uh and leveraging their manager to make
sure that they are.
Is that something that they're reluctant
to do or developers just aren't in the
habit of doing?
I'd say yes and yes.
We are introverts and we tend to dismiss
our skill sets, either either either
dismiss them or think or think they're
better than they are. So, it can go both
ways, but
our tendency then is to be quiet rather
than
communicative.
And one of the responsibilities of a
manager is to grow programmers into
communicating with the rest of the team
and communicating what they know and
communicating their expertise and
experience.
How can the manager surface those unique
skills and capabilities and get the
programmer to come out of their shell
and even progress further and blossom
into the best programmer they can be.
Yeah, so that's a that's a really
broad-ranging question. The The first
thing is is to form the relationship
with the programmer between the manager
and the programmer.
In order for us who are managers to know
who programmers are, we really have to
connect with them.
And we have to connect with who they are
and what they care about. And out of
that comes understanding of what they
know and what they can share.
Uh, you know, some of that's some of
that maybe even a lot of that's going to
come out in code, it's going to come out
in
conversation, it's going to come out
Well, it may come out. Depends on how
introverted people are. So, it will come
out in code. The question is, will we
recognize it when it comes out in code
from a programmer who's so introverted
that they sit in the corner instead of
engaging in conversation. Uh, and our
challenge is to find ways to get that
introverted programmer into the mix and
sharing. And part of it part of it is
simply acknowledging
the value that that person has. They may
be sitting in the corner because they
don't feel they have value.
Uh, or they may be sitting in the corner
because they feel like they've got
value, but they don't know how to
communicate it. And helping them to make
that and and sometimes it's helping them
to make that communication just
one-on-one first
before they make it with two other
people and then with four other people
and with eight other people. So, we
don't necessarily put them up at the
whiteboard in front of the organization
on day one. Uh, that's a transition.
I've heard some managers say that their
biggest challenge is sourcing the right
candidates.
Not every team is in a position that the
Bulls or the Lakers are into have the
best players knocking on their door, how
can you overcome that challenge
if you're not finding the right
candidates or you find that you're not
getting enough applicants?
Yeah, so I'm going to I'm going to step
back to a rule of thumb, which is
and and this is an interesting one
because Mickey and I have both had done
it by just as the most important rule of
thumb that we think applies to
programming managers and that is
we need to always be recruiting.
So, one of the one of the things is we
come out of being introverts, too, but
we have to network. We have to go to
meetups. We have to be out there talking
to people.
We need to be collecting business cards.
We need to be collecting LinkedIn
connections. We need to be connecting
with interviewees. We may interview a
bunch of people at one company and
select only one, but realize that there
are two or three others who are
interesting and our responsibility as
managers for the future is to stay in
touch with those other two or three
people who are also good programmers
to make them part of our network, to
build what is in some ways a hiring
network,
but is is certainly our personal network
and it's a network that we need that we
need to be able to leverage as hiring
managers in recruiting. So, that's one
part. Or maybe it's two parts. The third
one is that we need to not only always
be recruiting, but we need to be
thinking about what our core value is,
what our mission is, what our company is
contributing to the world. So, as an
engineer, I I've looked at my own and
I've looked at an awful lot of engineers
and an awful lot of us
are motivated by making a difference in
the world, possibly more motivated by
that than almost anything else.
You know, if we're being paid enough,
what motivates us to do great work? And
it's making a difference in the world.
It's It's
getting the light to come on in people's
eyes. It's delighting customers. It's
It's
uh you know, making a making a big
difference.
And we as managers need to think about
what's the difference that our company
is making. What's the difference that
our products are making. What's the
difference that my team is making. And
what's the difference that the person
that I'm hiring into this role can make
for our team and our customers and our
company and the world. And to be able to
communicate that. And I think that's a
really powerful
motivating recruiting message.
I'd like to try to summarize
the most important rule of thumb you
said was always be recruiting. And this
is the secret to hiring the right people
even if you otherwise
would have challenges in sourcing talent
for whatever reason.
And part of that too is finding out
what's motivating for you and for your
company. The There are values that
a candidate might share that would
motivate them
to take the job and also motivate them
in the job. And in fact, you gave a
whole chapter on the topic of
motivation. I'd love to talk more about
that later. First, I want to dive into
the day-to-day of what a manager's
job looks like. Could you talk a little
bit about maybe hour by hour
or as a a slice of the pie, where does a
manager spend their time?
In meetings.
Uh there's no question that where a
manager spends their time is in
meetings. And because of that, we need
to set aside thinking time, strategizing
time.
And to ensure that we've got innovative
thinking time. And to think about where
that is.
You know, where does a manager spend
their day? Well, I can tell you where I
spend the beginning of my day and that's
in the shower and taking a shower in the
morning is where I think through my day
and think about what difference I'm
going to make today and what impact I
can make and about the big challenges
I'm facing and what I'm going to do
about them today. That conversation with
myself happens in the shower in the
morning before I even get going.
And then I need to be in touch with the
people who work for me,
people who are in my group during the
day.
I need to be in touch with my peers and
I need to be in touch with my boss and
those are those are all meetings.
And then I am quite possibly going to be
involved in fomenting teamwork somewhere
or another
and making sure that the right people
are talking to each other about the
right issues.
And uh and there's a huge element of
what's called socialization of ideas
where I realize that the possible answer
is to this problem and that means I need
to talk to a whole bunch of people along
the way and begin socializing that
solution,
get people on board with that solution
and begin to build a consensus around
making that solution happen.
It sounds like you're keeping uh keeping
tabs on the big picture situation of
what people are thinking about, what
people are talking about, and trying to
make sure that the big important ideas
are shared across bunch of various
groups. Is that the right way to
interpret what you said?
So I'd say I'd say that's that's if not
yet, it's definitely part of it. I think
that the challenge is to make sure that
we're working on the most important
stuff.
And uh it's one of the things I love
about Agile is that Agile for project
teams
one of the basic practices is having a
backlog that's ordered by the things
that are the most important to do that
will deliver the most value to customers
that will delight our customers most.
And we need to think about our own work
in the same way. Creating that backlog
that's that we know that the thing I'm
going to work on next is the thing
that's going to deliver the most value.
Let's say as an example the thing at the
top of your backlog is
there's an idea that you need to
socialize amongst your team or teams.
Could Could you give an example of the
way that that socialization process
would work?
Yeah, I'll give you I'll give you an
example. So at a company I was at
we had a whole lot of teams across the
company
and we were doing very early work with
Java.
And in order to do very early work with
Java, application servers did not yet
exist or they did not exist in a robust
kind of way.
Which meant that we basically had to
engineer those ourselves. So we were in
the financial services business.
A financial services applications
development team engineering was
essentially system software is
not exactly how I would like application
developers to spend their time, but it
was what we had to do at the time
because application servers didn't
exist.
And so we would build them out of CORBA.
Which was hard and deep and and we had a
number of failures for that reason and
we had a number of successes that were
based on CORBA, but application servers
did come along. We did decide that we
did pick a couple that we wanted to base
that on and we
realized that we were we were moving
forward into the future in this
application server Java based direction,
but we had some older code based around
this CORBA stuff, and we needed to solve
this. One, we needed to stop building
CORBA based applications, and we needed
to stop having application developers
building CORBA infrastructure.
And two, we needed to think about as
those systems aged and needed to be
maintained or updated or especially when
they needed major improvements, what we
were going to do about that and how we
were going to move into the future.
This is not exactly an easy problem
because you've got a whole bunch of
people who are
tied to having done CORBA work and
having done good CORBA work. The ones
The ones that are in production are the
ones that are working.
They've got a vested interest in what it
what what it is they know and what it is
they were able to achieve, and I made it
a point
to
We had a cafeteria that was on the
center floor of the building, so 14
floors on the seventh floor is the
cafeteria, and everybody comes down to
the cafeteria somewhere between 11:30
and 1:00, and I made it a point to run
into the people who were connected to
CORBA and to say,
"I think we need to work through how
we're going to move forward relative to
this issue of CORBA and of application
servers and what we've got and what we
need to have and and just having that
conversation of not a solution,
really just presenting the fact that we
needed a solution. We needed to come
together as a group, and there were a
lot of stakeholders,
and I think I did that for about 6
months. Probably longer than my
management was happy about my doing
that, but at the point at which we came
together, we were already to have that
conversation. We walked into the room on
a Friday afternoon. and I had a room
reserved for 3 hours. We did a go around
and everybody talked with each other. We
shared what it was how we were connected
into the Corba universe and into the
Java universe and into the future
universe and in 2 hours we had we had
said, "Here's what we're going to do in
this case and this case and this case.
Here's how we can move forward." We had
unanimity
in 2 hours.
And it it's the kind of unanimity that
for a socializing manager makes shivers
run up and down your back because it
doesn't happen very often.
You were able to achieve consensus in
that 2-hour meeting, but it sounds like
a situation where
you could have made a decision and
impose it from the top down.
What would have been the outcome had you
done that?
People probably would have left. They
would have quit. They would have argued.
They would have fought. You know, there
would have been all kinds of angst and
and conflict and people would have
escalated to SVPs and EVPs and there
would have been a senior-level executive
meetings and it would have gone on and
on and on.
And the people who stayed behind, do you
think they would be motivated?
Not so much.
Is it the manager's job to keep the team
motivated?
So the answer is absolutely yes. Is the
manager the only person whose job it is
to keep the team motivated? Probably
not. But it it's certainly it's
certainly my job as a manager to make
sure that the people who work for me
have a clue, have an insight into the
impact that their work can make and can
do.
And that's you know, making an impact in
the world I cited earlier as as I think
one of the most motivating for those of
us in engineering, for those of us in in
programming,
for those of us working this craft of of
code, Uh know, I think making a
difference is is a huge piece.
And and then we need to look at making
sure we don't demotivate people.
And look and making sure that we've got
the other pieces of motivation in place.
So that it's a place that people want to
work. That So it's a place that people
have fun working.
So that it's a place where people come
together and feel like they're in a
second family.
So it's in that kind of place.
You talked about two broad categories of
motivating factors. The kind that can
demotivate people and the kind that can
elevate people.
Could you describe that a little bit
right now?
In the chapter on motivation, we
introduce three theories and we give
them only a page or two a piece.
But they're sort of fundamental to
understanding how people how our brands
work, how we're motivated as people. Um
this particular one is a is a guy named
Herzberg who and actually all three of
them were the 1940s and 1950s. The first
one everyone will recognize, which is
Maslow.
Um and Maslow's hierarchy of needs.
Um the second two are McGregor and
Herzberg. Herzberg posited that there
aren't as many things that motivate
people as we think.
One of those things that we think
motivates people is money. And his
contention was that there are two kinds
of motivators. One that are one set that
are foundational that if you don't have
them, you can't motivate you can't
really motivate people. And the other
and so we call those demotivators.
Um for lack when they're lacking,
they're demotivators. And the other set
are truly motivators. And so think about
company policies or respect for your
supervisor. So you know, most people
don't join companies because they
respect the person that they're hiring
in to report to you. And I don't know
anyone who's ever joined a company
because of its administrative policies.
But administrative policies can sure
make you leave a company. And there's an
HR rule of thumb that says that people
don't leave companies, they leave
managers.
If you don't have respect for your
manager, you are very highly likely to
leave.
So those are demotivators, and then
there are motivators, which, you know,
we tend to think, "Oh, let's put some
money in front of somebody." And you
know, this guy Daniel Pink has written a
whole book about how drive, it's the
name of his book, on well, one of the
one of the big themes of it is that
putting money in front of people in fact
is is counterproductive
as a motivator.
The things that motivate programmers,
and I'm going to turn to the turn to the
example,
the things that motivate programmers
tend to be making a difference in the
world. So he said achievement, but we
said making a difference in the world.
Learning and growing, toys and
technology, having fun,
recognition and praise. Those are those
are all things that motivate
programmers, and making sure that we're
recognizing the people on our teams,
that we're praising the people that are
on our teams, that they're connected
with the message of the
of the company and understand how
they're going to make a difference in
the world.
Uh that they continue learning and
growing as programmers. This is really
fundamental to who we are as
programmers. We want to continue
learning and growing in technology, and
we get to play with technology and have
fun with technology. Those are those are
really significant motivators.
That one is interesting. I'm looking at
the chart you're showing from your book
that ranks the motivators and
demotivators. The learning and growing
is unique because it's both a strong
motivator and a strong demotivator.
That's right. And having fun is is is as
well. If you're not having fun, you're
likely to leave. If you're having fun,
you're likely to stay.
And more fun is likely to be a
motivator. More learning and growing is
likely to be a motivator. No learning
and growing is likely to be a
demotivator. So, there are things that
are both motivators and demotivators.
And then there are things like
administrative policies that are just
demotivators.
We covered a lot of interesting
important material from your book, and I
want to start wrapping up. Ultimately,
who should and should not become a
manager?
Fundamentally, you want to think about
whether your career is about the people
who build technology or whether you want
your career to be about the building of
technology itself.
And I think And I think each of us has
to choose at that inflection point
where we have an opportunity to become a
manager, whether we want to continue
going up a technical ladder and stay
technical. And for many of us it's it's
a choice of I want to stay introverted.
I don't want to learn those extraversion
skills. I don't want to learn how to
motivate people. I This is not who I am.
I am about technology. And And I
certainly understand that. Especially
going back and forth as a programmer and
a manager three times at Apple,
it was a question I continued to ask
there for a while. And it was a
wonderful back and forth for me
because I was able to go back to being a
programmer and look at my manager and
how he was doing it with really new eyes
for having tried to be that manager
just a few weeks before.
And to think about what of what he's
doing can I leverage, and what are the
pressures pressures on him that I saw
myself
uh once I became a manager that I had no
idea of. And what are all of the things
that he has to do behind the scenes that
I don't see. I just look at him as oh,
he's my manager. He He's He's
responsible for my care and feeding, but
there's this
whole other uh set of things where where
managers are
actually working to help their managers
succeed,
who are uh working with their peers to
figure out stuff and to make the
organization succeed, and who are doing
a whole lot of other things besides just
my care and feeding.
Could you give an example of one of
those things or one of the things your
manager was doing that you didn't
appreciate before that you recognized
later?
Yeah, I think once you get into the area
of helping other people succeed, you
realize that your job is not just to
help the people that work for you
succeed. Your job is to help your boss
succeed.
Um there's a rule of thumb that says the
most important person in the
organization is your boss.
And this is a uh a significant
realization.
A second one of those is that it one of
the uncomfortable things you realize is
that whereas as a programmer, you were
pretty much judged on what you did,
as a manager, you're judged on how what
you do is perceived.
It is perception, not what you're doing,
and perception means that you have to
communicate what you're doing
to up and out so that people realize the
impact of what it is you're doing, and
you have to communicate that. Your job
becomes one of communication
way way way more than it ever was when
you were a programmer. You could just
rely on well, here's what I Well, here's
what I did. Here's my code. Here Here
are the lines of code. It's working.
So, it's about how what you're doing is
perceived by those above you. That's the
up. Your peers, that's the out.
And by the people who work for you.
people below you.
Yep.
Yes.
Some organizations only provide
management as a track towards promotion.
And
if as an engineer I want to grow my
career or get a raise, I might feel like
I'm forced into going into management.
Is that Is that something that you
found? And what's the impact of that?
Good organizations
starting decades and decades ago
recognized that that's a problem.
There are truly talented people who want
to grow their careers
and not grow their careers into
management. And those good organizations
created dual track
growth.
Dual dual track promotional
opportunities where people could stay on
the technical track or move into the
management track and move up through the
ranks.
Um there's no technical ladder CEO
position
that I've ever seen. There are CEOs
who've been technical, but but they are
CEOs, not some kind of parallel to a CEO
in a technical track.
But there's a role that goes all the way
up the ladder
to just below the CEO in good
organizations. And if if you want to
stay on a technical track, find an
organization that has a technical track.
I'd like to find out if there's any
important questions from your point of
view that I left out that I should ask
about management.
There's one aspect There's a low-hanging
fruit that if you're a manager, even if
you're on a team, there's a low-hanging
fruit that is plucked way too seldom in
technical organizations. I can't speak
about the rest, but it certainly in
technical organizations and product
organizations and that's onboarding.
We did a whole chapter on what to do
after you've recruited someone
between when they've accepted the offer
and when they're
maybe a month into the job and what that
transition looks like. So, there's two
parts to that. One is making sure the
person actually shows up for the first
day because they've been in the
recruiting cycle and there may be
somebody else after them who makes them
a better offer after they accepted yours
and there are
an awful lot of us who are managers who
have had the experience where we thought
we had someone hired and they didn't
show up on the first day or they showed
up just long enough to say, "Oh, by the
way, I accepted a counteroffer from my
former boss or I accepted a better offer
from some other company."
So, the care and feeding in between
accepting an offer and coming on board
is is significant and important. But,
secondly, onboarding itself, the first
day, the second day. So, HR does
onboarding and the benefits, but we need
to onboard people into teams.
So, I'm also the co-author of the study
of product team performance and
we
query
people on product teams all around the
world, the developers, product managers,
project managers, scrum masters,
everybody who are testers, everybody who
who are on product teams about
are they on a high-performance product
team or a low-performance product team
or average? How do they characterize
their team? And then what practices
how do they characterize their
practices? And one of the things that we
that was found in the first study. So, I
was not the co-author of the very first
year that the study was done and my
interest was so piqued that I made a
point of contacting the the co-authors
of it and then they
didn't have an engineering voice and
they had they recruited me to be part of
the team and it was an unexpected
I have I have another job now that I
wasn't expecting to have.
But,
the outcome of that first one was that
there were five characteristics of teams
that correlated with high-performance
teams, and one of them was effective
onboarding.
And so, that next year, when I was in my
first co-authorship year, we decided we
would ask teams about how effective was
their onboarding.
And the number of people on teams who
said that their onboarding could be
considered a best practice was 5%.
Given that onboarding correlates with
high-performance teams, and only 5% of
teams are willing to call out their
onboarding as effective, as a best
practice, this is a low-hanging fruit.
We need to onboard people onto our teams
better. We need to help people become
productive way faster and become part of
teams way faster.
I'll be sure to include a link to the
study in our show notes, as well as a
link to your book, and where else can
people find more information about you
and the work that you do?
Well, so I'm at ronlichty.com.
Uh our book is
managingtheunmanageable.net.
Uh you have to spell it right.
And uh and you'll find links to the
study uh from both of those, and and
links to stuff we do, and
a managerial training we do, and we have
Addison-Wesley recorded video training
based on the book. Uh all that stuff is
you can find out about off there. And uh
and you can also find more rules of
thumb. So, we've continued to collect
rules of thumb, and the additional rules
of thumb are are on uh on
managingtheunmanageable.net.
Thanks, Ron. The book is an incredible
resource. I enjoyed reading it. I I
encourage everyone to pick it up.
In addition to those rules of thumb, you
had
a set of tools at the of the book
including spreadsheets for
conducting interviews, making sure that
you're everyone's asking the right set
of consistent questions.
And for onboarding.
And for onboarding. Let's not forget a
whole chapter on onboarding. Uh Ron
Lichty, thanks for being on Software
Engineering Radio.
All right, thanks Nate.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.